Finding Aid for Todd Duncan papers, 1912-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Todd Duncan papers 1912-1998, 1935-1973
Duncan, Todd.
12 linear feet
2010225 Aa 2
The Todd Duncan Papers document the life and career of baritone singer Todd Duncan. Trained as a classical singer, Duncan was chosen by George Gershwin to originate the role of Porgy in Gershwin's American folk opera Porgy and Bess. Duncan's career spanned numerous concert tours, productions, and performances. The papers in the collection include photographs, scrapbooks, news stories, and personal papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Todd Duncan Papers were received in September 2008 through the University of Michigan Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (donor 10110 ).
No further additions to the collection are expected.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Robert Todd Duncan was born February 12, 1903, in Danville, Kentucky to John and Lettie Duncan. Music was a part of his life from an early age. His mother, a music teacher, began giving him piano lessons when he was five. Duncan credited the discovery of his vocal talent to a later piano teacher and it eventually replaced piano as his instrument of choice. At the age of 17, Duncan attended a Roland Hayes concert in Louisville, Kentucky. According to Duncan, he was so moved by the performance that he decided to pursue a vocal career. He attended high school at Simmons State University and earned his bachelor's degree from Butler University in 1925 and a M.A. from Columbia University Teacher's College in 1930. Following graduation, he moved to Washington, D.C. in 1931 to begin teaching music at Howard University. In 1934, he married Gladys Jackson, a Washington, D.C. schoolteacher.
Duncan received an invitation from George Gershwin in 1935 to audition for the American folk opera Gershwin was writing called Porgy and Bess. Duncan was initially unsure he wanted to be involved as he preferred classical singing and he considered Gershwin to be something of a "Tin Pan Alley" composer. The audition was successful and Duncan, moved by the music and the story, signed on for the opera. It opened in 1935 and ran for 124 shows. Porgy was the role Duncan became best known for and he performed the role over 1800 times between the original 1935 run and its 1942-1944 revival. It was during the 1942-1944 run that Duncan famously led the cast's refusal to perform at the National Theatre in Washington, D.C. because the audience was to be segregated with African-Americans regulated to balcony seating. The theatre and managers threatened to sue for contract negation if the actors did not perform but ultimately the protest was successful. The performance was desegregated, although permanent desegregation at the theatre did not occurs until the mid-1950s.
His further acting productions include two films Syncopation in 1941 and Unchained in 1955; for which the song Unchained Melody was originally produced. Duncan continued to perform on the stage as well and his other productions include The Sun Never Sets (1938) in London, Cabin in the Sky (1944), Lost in the Stars (1950), and Job (1972).
Duncan broke the race barrier in 1945 when he became the first African-American performer to perform at the Metropolitan Opera House. His role was that of Tonio in the opera I Pagliacci; a traditionally Caucasian role. Duncan performed with the New York City Opera in several operas. Duncan also had a successful concert career and toured from 1940 until his retirement in 1965. During his 25 year career, he visited more than 850 U.S. cities and over 50 countries on European, South American, and Australian tours. A longtime citizen of Washington, D.C., Duncan performed at the White House for President Eisenhower and President Roosevelt. He was a featured performer at Lyndon Johnson's Inaugural Concert in 1965.
In 1964, Duncan semi-retired, and began giving full-time private vocal lessons. He was known for his fundamental technique and for honing the individual talents of his students rather than teaching rigid vocal theory and performance. Duncan was an active member of the community and the arts. He served as the first president of the Washington Performing Arts Society from 1967 to 1970. Washingtonian Magazine named him Washingtonian of the year in 1977. Duncan continued to give lessons well into his nineties. He passed away in Washington, DC on February 28, 1998.
The Todd Duncan Papers consist of scrapbooks, photographs, news stories, production programs, and personal papers documenting the career and life of Todd Duncan. Many of the items are scrapbooks of Duncan's career and tours which feature newspaper clippings and photographs from the productions themselves. The collection came to the Bentley Library partially processed. That arrangement has been retained.
The collection spans the years from 1912 to 1998 with the majority of items falling between the years 1935-1973. The collection has ten series: Correspondence; Honors and Awards; Music Programs and Scores; Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks; Papers and Books; Photographs; Audio-Visual Materials; Productions and Performances; Topical Files; and African American Music Collection Numbered Items.
Subjects:
African American actors.; African American singers.; African American theater.; African Americans--Music.; Baritones (Singers); Duncan, Todd.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Porgy and Bess.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans.; Actors--United States.; Singers--United States.; Theatrical productions--United States.; African Americans--Music.; Duncan, Todd.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Porgy and Bess.; Weill, Kurt, 1900-1950--Lost in the stars.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1935-1993
  The Correspondence (0.15 linear feet) series covers the years 1935 to 1993 and contains letters, cards, and telegrams written to Todd Duncan. Interesting artifacts in this series include a letter from Maya Angelou and copies of letters sent from George Gershwin.
  - 1935-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1994 (Box 1)
  - Copies of Letters from George Gershwin to Todd Duncan 1935, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Duncan to Eva Jessye undated (Box 1)
  - Envelopes undated (Box 1)
  - Maya Angelou to Todd Duncan 1993 (Box 1)
- Honors and Awards 1950-1983
  The Honors and Awards series (.25 linear feet) series is dated between the years 1950 and 1983. This series holds certificates, awards, and honorary degrees awarded to Todd Duncan over his career. Several items in this series are oversize and are housed in oversize boxes.
  - General, 2 folders (Box 11)
    [one oversize folder in Box 11]
  - 1959 Democratic National Victory Dinner Guest List, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc. 1952 (Box 11)
    [oversize, in Box 11]
  - Americans for Democratic Action 1950 (Box 1)
  - Association of Professional Vocal Ensembles Meritorious Service Award 1984 (Box 12)
    [oversize, in Box 12]
  - Berea College Honorary Doctorate of Music 1983 (Box 1)
  - Central State College Honorary Degree of Music 1958 (Box 1)
  - Citation Read by the President of Howard University in Awarding the Honorary Degree of Doctor of Music to Todd Duncan 1956 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Teacher's College Distinguished Alumnus Award 1978 (Box 1)
  - Curtis Institute of Music -- Honorary Doctorate of Music 1985 (Box 12)
  - Gladys Duncan -- Citizen's Council of the District of Columbia Certificate 1962, 1963 (Box 12)
  - Howard University 1981 (Box 1)
  - National Symphony Orchestra Recognition of Todd Duncan's 90th year 1993 (Box 12)
  - Philip Murray -- William Green Award 1972 (Box 1)
  - President's Dinner 1983 (Box 1)
  - Valparaiso University 1950 (Box 1)
  - Valparaiso University Honorary Doctorate of Music Diploma (Box 11)
  - Washingtonian of the Year Plaque 1977 (Box 12)
  - Women's Committee of the Washington Performing Arts Society Salute to Todd Duncan 75th Birthday 1978 (Box 1)
- Music Programs and Scores 1925-1964
  The Music Programs and Scores series (.15 linear feet) encompasses the years from 1925 to 1964. Items in this series include programs from Duncan's concert tours, operas, productions, and performances. It also has a small number of musical scores either used or collected by Duncan. Of note is a musical score marked original score of "Unchained Melody."
  - Assorted Programs 1949-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Assorted Scores 1925-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - Assorted Scores undated (Box 11)
    [oversize, [in Box 11]
  - Celebrity News, Programme by Todd Duncan, Winnipeg Auditorium 1949 (Box 1)
  - Lost in the Stars 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Original Score for "Unchained Melody" undated (Box 1)
  - Tours Abroad, 1945-1955 (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks 1935-1991
  The Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbook series (1.0 linear feet), 1935-1991, is comprised of scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, official press releases, and publications documenting Duncan's career including his European Tours Porgy and Bess production, and performances. Also of interest are several family and personal scrapbooks. Some items in this series are oversize and are housed in oversize boxes 11 and 12.
  - 75th Birthday Celebration 1978 (Box 1)
  - 1945 European Tour Press Notices (Box 1)
  - 1946 New Zealand and Australia Tours, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1947 British Tour (Box 1)
  - 1947 British Tour Poster (Box 1)
    [in Box 12 OVERSIZE]
  - 1947 European Tour (Box 1)
  - Assorted Clippings 1935-1984, 3 folders (Box 1)
    [one folder in Box 11 oversize]
  - Bravo Magazine Article, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Concert Career 1951-1961 (Box 1)
  - Concert Tours (copies) 1945-1950, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Current Biography Magazine, 1942 (Box 1)
  - European Concert Tour 1943-1955 (Box 1)
  - Family and Friends Scrapbook 1965-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Newstories from Tours Abroad 1945, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, Concert Tours, and Reviews 1944-1977 (Box 2)
  - Porgy and Bess Scrapbook, 1935-1938, 1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Press Book Melbourne 1946 (Box 2)
  - Press Story on Todd Duncan Supplied by Community Concert Service 1963 (Box 2)
  - Productions and Concert Tours 1943-1958 (Box 2)
  - "The Sun Never Sets" 1938 (Box 2)
  - "Todd Duncan the First Stephen Kumalo," 1972 (Box 2)
  - Tours Abroad 1945, 1947, 1954, 1957 (Box 2)
- Papers and Books 1912-1986
  The Papers and Books series (1.0 linear feet) covers the years 1912-1986. It includes early school report cards, diplomas, production scripts, books, and items collected by Duncan such as date books and magazines.
  - Application for Teacher's License -- State of Indiana 1925 (Box 2)
  - Butler College Report Card 1923-1924 (Box 2)
  - Butler University Diploma 1925 (Box 2)
  - "The Crisis," 1925 (Box 2)
  - Date Book 1925 (Box 2)
  - Date/Sketch Book 1916-1920 (appx.) (Box 2)
  - George Gershwin Le Musicien de la "Rhapsody in Blue," 1948 (Box 2)
  - Family Passports 1938, 1945 (Box 2)
  - "The Guide," 1960 (Box 2)
  - "Lost in the Stars" Script undated (Box 2)
  - Marian Anderson undated (Box 2)
  - Music and the American Family undated (Box 2)
  - Report Cards 1912-1917 (Box 2)
  - Simmonia, Simmons University Yearbook 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Simmonia, Simmons University Yearbook 1921-1922 (Box 2)
  - Simmons University Annual Commencement Program May 31, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Simmons State University Diploma 1921 (Box 11)
  - Simmons State University Diploma 1922 (Box 11)
  - Sketches of Todd Duncan undated (Box 2)
  - State University-Louisville, Kentucky undated, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Syncopation Script, 1941 (Box 2)
- Photographs 1930-1983
  The Photograph series (.75 linear feet) contains photographs falling between the years 1930 and 1983. Included are photographs of family and friends and productions. There is also a folder of photographs of other actors and actresses autographed to Duncan. The series has a sub-series which contains those photographs specifically featuring Duncan.
  - Autographed to Todd Duncan 1930-1977 (Box 3)
  - Autographed to Todd Duncan undated (Box 11)
  - Charles Duncan undated (Box 3)
  - Duncan Teaching a Class undated (Box 3)
  - Family and Friends undated (Box 11)
  - Family and Friends 1930-1983, undated (Box 3)
  - Gladys Duncan undated (Box 3)
  - Lyndon Johnson (Box 3)
    [in Box 11 OVERSIZE]
  - Porgy and Bess Production, undated (Box 3)
  - Posters undated (Box 11)
  - Syncopation Movie Stills, 1941
  - Todd Duncan
    - Assorted Negatives (Box 3)
    - Black and White Headshots (Box 3)
    - Concerts (Box 3)
    - Group Shots (Box 3)
    - Lost in the Stars (Box 3)
    - Performances (Box 3)
    - Performances (Box 11)
    - Posed Photographs (Box 3)
    - Posed Photographs (Box 11)
      [in Box 11 oversize]
    - Rehearsing Porgy and Bess with Gershwin and Cast (Box 3)
    - The Sun Never Sets (Box 3)
    - Unchained Movie Stills, 1955 (Box 3)
- Productions and Performances 1949-1998, 1965
  The Productions and Performances series (.25 linear feet) falls between the years 1949 and 1998. This series houses items dealing specifically with productions and performances involving Duncan. Items of interest include handbills, programs, and papers.
  - 1965 Inaugural Concert -- Lyndon Johnson (Box 3)
  - Concert Tour Handbill 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Lost in the Stars, 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess Programs, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess, 1942, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess Spring Production, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess: An American Voice," 1998 (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess the Beginnings, undated (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Materials series includes four 16mm films of family and friends.
  - Family Films undated (4 16mm films) (Box 3)
- Topical Files 1984-1998
  The Topical Files series (.10 linear feet) covers the years 1984-1998. The small series contains items on Duncan and his wife's lives. Items of interest in this series include Duncan's obituary and the program from his funeral.
  - Biography Materials 1984 (Box 3)
  - Gladys Duncan a Centenary Anniversary 1996 (Box 3)
  - Obituary and Memorial Service Program 1998 (Box 3)
  - Recital Program from the Studio of Todd Duncan undated (Box 3)
- African American Music Collection Numbered Items
  The African American Music Collection Numbered Items (7.0 linear feet) series contains those items processed prior to transfer. The series has some overlap with earlier series and duplication is expected. Items include newspaper clippings, papers, books, programs, photographs, and correspondence, to name a few.
  - Items 1-125 (Box 4)
  - Items 535-1228 (Box 5)
  - Items 1251-1958 (Box 6)
    [See Box 12 oversize for items 1305-1319]
  - Items 1959-2801 (Box 7)
  - Items 2988-3650 (Box 8)
  - Items 3652-3819 (Box 9)
  - Items 3831-4587 (Box 10)
    [See Box 12 oversize for items 3651, 4013-1087]
- Oversize Material
  (Items are listed above)
  - Oversize Material (Box 11)
  - Oversize Material (Box 12)
    (continued)